<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of Mr. Parkinson's expulsion from the University of Oxford in the late times in vindication of him from the false aspersions cast on him in a late pamphlet entituled, The history of passive obedience.</title>
            <author>Parkinson, James, 1653-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11774</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13798497</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13798497</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56408)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 470:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of Mr. Parkinson's expulsion from the University of Oxford in the late times in vindication of him from the false aspersions cast on him in a late pamphlet entituled, The history of passive obedience.</title>
                  <author>Parkinson, James, 1653-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Purportedly by an observer of the case, but according to Anthony Wood and DNB was published anonymously by Parkinson.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parkinson, James, 1653-1722.</term>
               <term>Seller, Abednego, 1646?-1705. --  History of passive obedience since the Reformation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101879:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF Mr. <hi>PARKINSON</hi>'s Expulſion From the UNIVERSITY OF OXFORD In the Late TIMES.</p>
            <p>In Vindication of him from the Falſe Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions caſt on him in a late Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>The Hiſtory of Paſſive Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for, and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:101879:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101879:2"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF Mr. <hi>PARKINSON</hi>'s Expulſion From the UNIVERSITY of <hi>OXFORD</hi> In the Late Times.</head>
            <p>ONE might well have expected, That Mr. <hi>P.</hi> who was illegally expell'd the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and thereby depriv'd of his Fellowſhip in <hi>Lincoln</hi> College in the late Times, would, upon his reſtitution to the Univerſity, have been immediately invited to return to his College. Or, if 'twere too much to expect That, yet one might in reaſon have thought, that none of the College would have oppos'd his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to it: eſpecially conſidering, that even thoſe, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly were his Accuſers, are now in their Opinions come over to him; or at leaſt have acted by thoſe very Principles, which they accus'd him of maintaining. Now methinks they ſhould in reaſon do one of theſe two things; Either ſtill reject his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, or receive Him. For not to admit him, when they have admitted his Principles, is as much againſt the Rules of good Logick, as 'tis, when they have granted the Premiſes, to deny the Concluſion. The Reverend Dr. <hi>Ironſide,</hi> late Vice-Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>Oxford,</hi> (now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Briſtol</hi>) reſtor'd him to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101879:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Univerſity above ſix Months ago; and why the Rector and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of <hi>Lincoln</hi> College have not yet readmitted him to his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, I believe they can no more tell, than Dr. <hi>H.</hi> can, why he expell'd him the Univerſity. I'm ſure he ought to be readmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and ſince the College cannot yet be brought to do him right, (though I doubt not but in time they will) I'll endeavour to do him what right I can by Printing his Caſe, and telling the World how he was wrong'd.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> was a Maſter of Arts, and Fellow of <hi>Lincoln</hi> College in <hi>Oxford:</hi> the Fellowſhip he had there, is limited to the County of <hi>Oxford;</hi> ſo that none, but an <hi>Oxfordſhire</hi> Scholar, is capable of it. And there is this further to be obſerv'd concerning it, That the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> for the time being, (who is Viſitor of that College) has a peculiar right of nomination to it, whenever it is vacant. And accordingly he, being an <hi>Oxfordſhire</hi> Scholar, was nominated to this Fellowſhip by Biſhop <hi>Fuller,</hi> in the Year 1674. and admitted to it by the Rector and Fellows of the College.</p>
            <p>There he liv'd comfortably for nine years; and being a Tutor, had for ſome years above twenty young Schloars (at a time) under his care; inſomuch, that by his Fellowſhip, and advantage of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils, he had a yearly Income of 120 <hi>l.</hi> and there, it is thought, he might have liv'd to this day, had he not had ſo many Pupils. 'Twas the taking of Pupils that chiefly induc'd him to ſtay in that College ſo long, (the Fellowſhip alone being hardly ſufficient to maintain him there;) and 'twas, perhaps, the taking of too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that mov'd ſome of the Fellows to drive him from thence: (I ſay, ſome of the Fellows, for no more than four out of twelve were his Accuſers:) This probably was his greateſt fault; a fault, which he was never careful to mend, nor they willing to forgive.</p>
            <p>But they pretended a more ſpecious cauſe for their violent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of him: they gave it out, That he was a diſloyal Man, and diſaffected to the Government: and indeed, if to have other, notions of the Government, than they had, were to be diſloyal, it muſt be own'd Mr. <hi>P.</hi> was ſo: for he was willing to think and ſpeak of the Government as the Lawyers taught him, who, he believ'd, beſt underſtood it; but they were ſo wiſe as to correct the Law by their Miſtakes in Divinity. They thought <hi>the King was Abſolute;</hi> he was of another opinion. They ſaid, <hi>The Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101879:3"/>Power was lodg'd ſolely in the King;</hi> he believ'd it was not: <hi>They were againſt the Bill of Excluſion,</hi> he was for it. <hi>They were for Dr.</hi> Hick<hi>'s Paſſive Obedience,</hi> he was for Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi>'s. Now a difference between him and them about ſuch Points as theſe, one may eaſily gueſs, would cauſe frequent Diſputations and Quarrels; and a little ill Nature prompts men to undo thoſe whom they quarrel with, provided they have opportunity.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Adverſaries had as fair an opportunity for undoing of him; as their hearts could wiſh. For, mark the time when they began to complain of him: it was in the Year 1683, at that very time, when the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> Collonel <hi>Sidney,</hi> and other Gentlemen of Eminent Note, were ſeiz'd on, and ſens to the <hi>Tower</hi> for their zeal in oppoſing Popery, and Arbitrary Power: it was then, when the Nation was in a great ferment; when mens Paſſions were high, and made a great noiſe, ſo that Reaſon could not be heard. This was a lucky time for Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and of this Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Adverſaries took the advantage.</p>
            <p>Having got ſo fair an opportunity for oppreſſing him, they firſt apply'd themſelves to the Reverend Dr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> Rector of the College, and fill'd his Ears with Complaints againſt him. The Rector, who well knew that 'twas not any concern for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but rather Ill-will, and Self-intereſt, which ſet them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, endeavour'd to check their Heat, and bring them to ſome temper; but the more he labour'd to quiet them, the more outrageous they grew: They knew they had, what they call'd, the Government on their ſide; and that if the Rector would not receive their Complaints againſt one, whom they had every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſet out as a <hi>Whig,</hi> there were others that would. They made grievous Complaints of the Rector himſelf for refuſing to do them juſtice (as they phras'd it;) and gave it out, <hi>That he deſerv'd to be turn'd out of the College for favouring Mr.</hi> P.</p>
            <p>The Rector hereupon thought fit to appoint a Meeting of the Society, about the end of <hi>July</hi> 1683, for the hearing of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and gave him notice of it. It fell out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily for him, that many of the Fellows, (and thoſe too of beſt note) were then abſent from the College, (as is uſual in the Long Vacation) who, had they been there, it is likely would have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd his Adverſaries to let the matter fall, and to forbear proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting one of their Fellow-members.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101879:4"/>A Meeting then there was of the Society at the time appointed; and Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Adverſaries having drawn up their Charge againſt him, were pleas'd to read it to him. He perceiving that ſome things laid to his Charge were not material, had they been true; that ſome were very falſe; and that others wanted only a fair In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation to make them paſs; deſir'd a Copy of their Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and promis'd within a day or two to give them his Anſwer to it in writing. The Rector likewiſe requeſted the ſame in his behalf; but neither of them could prevail. The Rector per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that he could not gain any thing of them that was fair, and reſolving not to comply with them in any thing that was ſoul, nor to paſs an unjuſt cenſure upon him (which they preſs'd him to do) diſſolv'd the Meeting.</p>
            <p>Finding now that they could not work on the Rector, nor gain his concurrence for oppreſſing of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> they applied themſelves to Dr. <hi>H.</hi> a Provice-Chancellor, and complain'd that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had in their Company (ſome Months before) maintain'd ſeveral falſe and dangerous Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Doctor ſent for him, <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 20th, and told him, <hi>That ſome of the Fellows of</hi> Lincoln College <hi>had made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt him.</hi> He deſired to know who were his Accuſers, and what they laid to his Charge, and to have a Copy of their Accuſation, and promis'd his Anſwer to it. The Doctor ſaid, <hi>'Twas fit he ſhould know his Accuſers, and have a Copy of their Accuſation,</hi> and promis'd him both. And it muſt be own'd, that this was fair dealing in the Doctor; but tho he was ſo fair as to make this promiſe, yet he was not ſo juſt as to keep it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 24th, the Doctor ſent for him again, and tho he would neither let him know who were his Accuſers, nor what they laid to his Charge; yet he requir'd him forthwith to give Bail of 2000 <hi>l.</hi> for his good Behaviour, and Appearance at the next Aſſizes, which were to begin at <hi>Oxford</hi> on the 3d of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> following.</p>
            <p>I will not here blame the Doctor for denying Mr. <hi>P.</hi> a Copy of his Accuſation, nor yet for exacting ſo extravagant a Bail; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe how unreaſonable ſoever theſe things may ſeem, yet they were agreeable to thoſe times, and herein he did but write after the many ill Copies that were ſet him by others. But I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101879:4"/>forbear complaining of him for this one thing, (becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I think he followed no example) that, when Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had named for his Bail two Scholars, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and Mr. <hi>K.</hi> both Maſters of Arts, and Fellows of Colleges, and of as good note as any in the Univerſity, he refus'd them both, and yet would give no reaſon for his refuſing of them. It ſeem'd ſomewhat hard to Mr. <hi>P.</hi> that two of his own Body, the Univerſity, ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd, and that without any reaſon given; and that he ſhould ſtill be forced to name others. But this, how hard ſoever it was, he was forc'd to comply with, and to try again if he could hit the Doctor's humour in naming two others; which he had the good luck to do: For gueſſing, that no Scholars would paſs with him, he nam'd two of the Town, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and Mr. <hi>C.</hi> who were accepted for his Bail; and he was diſmiſs'd, having been kept Priſoner by the Doctor ſeveral hours, till his Sureties came to releaſe him.</p>
            <p>At the next <hi>Oxford</hi> Aſſizes, begun <hi>September</hi> the 3d. 1683. Mr. <hi>Philip Burton</hi> came to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and exhibited an Indictment againſt Mr. <hi>P.</hi> for maintaining the Propoſitions following (which I here preſent the Reader with, together with ſome remarks on each of them).</p>
            <p n="1">l. <hi>That 'tis lawful to exclude the next Heir to the Crown front his Right and Title to the Succeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe his Accuſers mean, as he did, ſuch an Excluſion, as had not long before been debated in Parliament, and had paſs'd the Honourable Houſe of Commons in two or three Parliaments ſucceſſively. Now ſuch an Excluſion as this, no doubt, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> held to be lawful, and, as I believe, two third parts of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion held it as well as he; tho' I never yet heard of any, beſides him, that had the ill luck to be impeach'd for it. The Law, I'm ſure, ſays, That the King, Lords and Commons, have right to limit and bind the Crown of this Realm, and the Deſcent, Inheritance, and Government thereof; as appears by the 13th of Queen <hi>Elizabeth, Cap.</hi> 1. by which Statute it was made Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, during the life of that Queen, to hold, affirm, or maintain the contrary; and, after her deceaſe, forfeiture of Goods and Chattels: And me thinks 'tis ſomewhat ſtrange, that it, ſhould be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101879:5"/>High Miſdemeanour in Mr. <hi>P.</hi> to ſpeak as the Law does. If Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>H.</hi> knew nothing of this Law, one would think his Friend Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> ſhould have inſtructed him in it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That if a Prince did not perform his duty, the Subjects might be diſcharged of theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> denies, that lie ever affirm'd any ſuch general Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And I can't but obſerve, that I have heard Dr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> who was then Rector of <hi>Lincoln</hi> College, more than once affirm, That at that Meeting held in the College about the end of <hi>July,</hi> (which I ſpake of before) and held on purpoſe for hearing of Complaints againſt Mr. <hi>P.</hi> there was not the leaſt mention made of this Propoſition. And Mr. <hi>P.</hi> dares affirm upon Oath, That he heard nothing of it at that Meeting; and therefore 'tis likely they had not thought of this to object againſt him at that time, it being not probable they would have concealed it, had they known arty thing of it. Nor is it a hard matter to gueſs how they came by it; for one may ſee it word for word, among the twenty-ſeven Propoſitions that the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on the 21ſt of <hi>July</hi> 1683. it being indeed a pare of the ſecond Propoſition in the Decree of that Univerſity. And 'tis likely, that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had never been accus'd for maintaining this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if that Univerſity had not firſt condemned it. I think, I am not bound to ſpeak my thoughts concerning this Propoſition; but however, out of meer love to Truth, I will ſay thus much, That in ſome Conſtitutions of Government, and in ſome Caſes, I believe it is true, <hi>if the Prince not only does not perform his duty, but acts alſo exorbitantly to the contrary.</hi> And becauſe Truth is then beſt, when 'tis rightly apply'd, I will venture to apply this to our preſent Caſe, and ſay, That <hi>the late King</hi> James <hi>having not done his duty, (but the contrary) the ſtiffeſt of the</hi> Jacobites (<hi>Mr.</hi> P.<hi>'s Accuſers not excepted) may be diſcharged of theirs, and may honeſtly (without diſtinctions, or equivocations, or mental reſervations) take the new Oath of Allegiance to our Gracious Sovereigns King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the King might be for ever laid aſide, ſo that there ſhould never more be a King of</hi> England <hi>for the future, by the Conſent of King, Lords, and Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101879:5"/>One fault I'm ſure there is in this propoſition, That 'tis ſillily worded: Now methinks 'tis ſomewhat hard to bring an informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Mr. <hi>P.</hi> for an uncouth expreſſion, if he had been guilty of it. There is in the words, 1. Something ſuppos'd, and that is, a conſent of the King, Lords, and Commons, That the King ſhould be for ever laid aſide, ſo that there ſhould never more be a King of <hi>England</hi> for the future; which is a very wild ſuppoſition, it being not in the leaſt probable that ever the thing ſuppoſed ſhould happen. And 2. there is ſomething affirm'd upon this unlikely ſuppoſition, and that is, That the King might be for ever laid aſide, ſo that there ſhould never more be a King of <hi>England</hi> for the future, in caſe there were ſuch a conſent. Now whether this be true, or no, let thoſe judge who will; for my part I hardly think it worth my while to examine it.</p>
            <p>I doubt few will believe that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> was indicted for theſe matters, unleſs I publiſh a Copy of the Indictment; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that, ſuch as it is, here follows:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="indictment">
                        <head>
                           <hi>A Copy of the Indictment.</hi> Ad Aſſiſas Autumnal 35. Car. 2di Regis.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>JUrati pro Dom.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Oxon.</note> 
                           <hi>Rege Super Sacrament. ſuum praeſentant,
quòd Jacobus P. De Oxon in Com Oxon. Clericus timorem dei in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſuo non habens, &amp;c. primo die Auguſti, Anno Regni dicti Dom. noſtri Caroli 2di, &amp;c. triceſimo quinto apud Oxon praedict. in Com. proedict. ex ſua prava mente &amp; nequiſſima Machinatione, in praeſentia &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditu quam plurimor ſubditor. dicti Dom. Regis tunc &amp; ibid. praeſentium, de dicto Dom. Rege &amp; gubernatione, &amp; regimine ſuis hujus Regni faeliciſſimis falſo malitioſe nequiter Diabolice &amp; Seditioſe dixit, aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit, declaravit, &amp; pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>palavit,</hi> Quod licitum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uit praecludere Proximum haeredem à titulo &amp; Succeſſione ſuis ad coronam. Et Quod ſi princeps (dict. Dom. Regem nunc innuendo) debitum ejus Anglice duty non performaret, ſubditi (ſubditos dicti Dom. Regis nunc innuendo) ab eorum exonerentur. Et quod Rex (dictum Dominum Regem nunc innuendo) in perpetuum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluderetur,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101879:6"/>Anglice <hi>laid aſide,</hi> ita quod in futuro nunquam Rex eſſet, Anglice <hi>a King in</hi> Anglia, per conſenſum Regis, Domino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; Communium in Parliamento. <hi>Ea intentione &amp; propoſito incitare &amp; movere populum hujus Regni Angliae ad odium &amp; diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationem Anglice</hi> diſlike <hi>perſonae dicti Domini Regis &amp; gubernationis ſtabiltae hujus Regni Angliae, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>E. H.</hi> Teſtes.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>R. F.</hi> Teſtes.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>A. T.</hi> Teſtes.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>T. W.</hi> Teſtes.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>To this Indictment Mr. <hi>P.</hi> (as well he might) pleaded Not Guilty; and his Trial was put off till the following Aſſizes, that is, till the following Lent. And now he thought himſelf ſafe till Lent came, the Trial being put off till that time; and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſafe he was by the <hi>Political Law;</hi> but on a ſudden Dr. <hi>Hicks</hi>'s <hi>Imperial Law</hi> laid hold on him, and condemn'd him before his Trial came: For the very day after he had pleaded Not Guilty, Dr. <hi>H.</hi> the Pro-Vice-Chancellor ſent for him, and told him, <hi>He muſt expel him the Univerſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> thought it ſomewhat ſtrange, That the Doctor ſhould firſt ſend him to the Aſſizes, to be Tried there; and then ſhould on a ſudden call him back, and Condemn him without ſo much as the formality of a Tryal. He ſaid, <hi>That the matter was then under a Judicial examination, and he hop'd the Doctor would wait the iſſue of that, and not paſs a more grievous judgment upon him, whil'ſt the matter ſtood indifferent, than in probability the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Law would be, in caſe he were found guilty upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment.</hi> He further deſir'd, <hi>That in caſe the Doctor were reſolv'd to proceed immediately, He would himſelf firſt hear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctor's Anſwer was, <hi>That he had Orders from above to expel him.</hi> To this Mr. <hi>P.</hi> replied, <hi>That ſurely he miſtook his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; That poſſibly he might have Orders to Try, but not to Condemn him without a Tryal; or if he had receiv'd any ſuch illegal Orders, he ought not to obey them; That he knew of no Orders that could turn him out of the Univerſity, and conſequently out of his Fllowſhip; That his Fellowſhip was his Freehold, and none could turn him out of his freehold, but by Law. And therefore he deſir'd the Pro-Vice-Chancellor
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101879:6"/>Chancellor to ſay, by what Law he proceeded.</hi> 'Twas no eaſie matter to gain the Doctor's Anſwer to this untoward queſtion: But at length he gave this, <hi>That he proceeded by the Laws or Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Univerſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Mr. <hi>P.</hi> Replied, <hi>That theſe indeed were Laws which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd him, and that he might have Proceeded againſt him by theſe Laws at firſt, if he had ſo pleaſed; but that now he fairly could not, having already bound him over to the Aſſizes, and begun a Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him at Common Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then Mr. <hi>P.</hi> deſired him to ſay, <hi>by what particular Statute of the Univerſity he proceeded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Anſwer was. <hi>by the Statutes de Contumeliis compeſcendis,</hi> and <hi>de Perturbatoribus Pacis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Mr. <hi>P.</hi> Replied, <hi>that ſurely it ought to be proved that he had utter'd contumelious words, and to be made out, that he had been a diſturber of the peace; which had not yet been done: For he had not been ſo much as examin'd concerning any matters laid to his charge; he had not been heard; he had not had his Accuſers face to face, nor any licenſe to anſwer for himſelf concerning the Crimes laid againſt him: And 'twas not agreeable to any Law, whether Divine or Humane, whether Civilt, or Common, or Statute Law, to Condemn any one before he was heard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 'twas in vain to diſpute with one who reſolv'd to obey Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; for the Doctor anſwer'd alt Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Arguments (and 'twas indeed the beſt anſwer he could give) by telling him, <hi>That he had Orders from above to expel him.</hi> And accordingly he did forthwith expel him the Univerſity in an arbitrary manner; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never heard him, nor ſo much as ſummon'd him to a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>H.</hi> it ſeems thought it a point of Loyalty to obey Orders; but I can tell him of as Loyal perſons as he is, who would not have thought ſo. What does he think of the Seven Biſhops that were ſent to the Tower? Were they for obeying Orders? What thinks he of the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi>'s behaviour in Dr. <hi>Sharp</hi>'s Caſe? Was not his Lordſhip bid to ſuſpend that Reverend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? and did his L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſhip do as be was bid? Did not hit Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip chuſe rather to be Suſpended himſelf, than to Suſpend a Dean of the Church in an illegal manner? True Loyalty al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101879:7"/>ways keeps pace with Juſtice, but never outruns it; nor is it to be thought Loyalty to undo a Fellow-Subject at the command of ones Prince.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="expulsion_order">
                        <head>A Copy of the Expulſion.</head>
                        <p>TImotheus Halton Sacrae Theologiae Profeſſor &amp; Univerſitatis Oxon. Pro Vice-Cancellarius omnibus literas haſce inſpecturis ſalutem. Cum ex juramentis quam plurimorum teſtium fide digno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oram nobis ſuſceptis Jacobus Parkinſon A. M. &amp; Coll. Lincolni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis Socius verba contumelioſa in ſereniſſimum Dominum noſtrum Carolum ſecundum Regem Angliae ad pacem &amp; concordiam Regni im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediendam, &amp; ad lites &amp; tumultus fovend. in contemptum Domini Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, coronae, dignitatis legumque ſuarum, &amp; in aliorum in tali caſu delinquentium incitamentum malitioſe &amp; ſeditioſe protuliſſe, eoque nomine contra bonos mores, jus hujus Regni commune, &amp; Statuta iſtius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitatis notorie deliquiſſe convictus ſit: Nos ut paci pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae &amp; diſciplinae Academicae (quantum in nobis eſt) proſpiciamus, &amp; gliſcenti in dies Seditioſorum licentiae obviemus, praedictum Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum Parkinſon tanquam pacis &amp; publicae tranquillitatis perturbatorem (juxta ſtatuti in ea partes editi exigentiam) ex iſta Univerſitate Oxon. expellimus bannimus &amp; exterminamus; ac expulſum, banni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; exterminatum tenore praeſentium denunciamus, atque omnibus Univerſitatis iſtius privilegiis penitus exutum declaramus. Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantes inſuper eidem Jacobo P. ut intra ſeptem dies proxime ſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes publicationem praeſentium extra iſtam Univerſitatem Oxon. ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que praecinctus ſe recipiat, in poſterum non reverſurum ſub poena juris ſi poſt dictos ſeptem dies intra Univerſatem iſtam ejuſve praecinctus, aut dicta circumcirca milliaria deprehenſus fuerit quacunque de cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, niſi in jus legitime vocatus, in quorum omnium fidem Sigillum officii Cancellariatus Univerſitatis Oxon. praeſentibus appoſuimus. Dat. apud Oxon. ſexto die menſis Septembris, Anno Dom. <hi>1683.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I cannot chuſe but obſerve here theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this Expulſion was grounded upon an Allegation which was not true; namely, That Mr. <hi>P.</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>victed of ſpeaking reproachful Words againſt the Government, whereas indeed he was never tried, nor convicted.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101879:7"/>2. That Dr. <hi>H.</hi> did not mention what thoſe reproachful Words were.</p>
            <p>Now this Expulſion of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> from the Univerſity, implying an Expulſion from his College, drew on him two very great Loſſes, the loſs of his Fellowſhip, and the loſs of his Pupils in <hi>Lincoln</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, to the value of 120 <hi>l. per ann.</hi> (which Loſſes he has ſuffer'd theſe ſix years.)</p>
            <p>And now one would have thought, That Dr. <hi>H.</hi> having expell'd him the Univerſity, would however have ſuffer'd him to breathe quietly in ſome other Air; and having forbidden him to come within five miles of <hi>Oxford,</hi> would have diſturb'd him no more, provided he had kept his due diſtance from the forbidden Place. But the Doctor did not think fit to do his work by halves. And therefore having unjuſtly expell'd Mr. <hi>P.</hi> the Univerſity, and ſtripe him of all that he bad, and made him poor, and bare, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, he took effectual care to keep him ſo; he ſtill kept him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the laſh of the Indictment, and forc'd him to attend ſeveral Aſſizes at <hi>Oxford;</hi> not that he ever intended that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſhould be brought to his Trial; (for he well knew, that the trying of one at the Aſſizes, whom he had condemn'd without a Trial, would not be much for his Credit) but this he did partly to expoſe him more and more, and ſhew him as a Criminal to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try every half year; partly to put him to great Expence and Charges, that thereby he might the ſooner conſume that little Treaſure he had laid up; but chiefly to hinder him from getting any other Preferment; rightly concluding, That none would venture to prefer one who was under an Indictment for High Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanor.</p>
            <p>And after all this, when the Doctor was even aſhamed to give him any more trouble, and put him to any further Charge in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the Aſſizes at <hi>Oxford;</hi> Matters were ſo manag'd (whether by Dr. <hi>H.</hi> or by Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> I will not ſay) that the Indictment was remov'd by <hi>Certiorari</hi> to the <hi>King's-Bench.</hi> And there Mr. <hi>P.</hi> appear'd before Chief Juſtice <hi>Jefferies,</hi> who having treated him as he us'd to do others, and paſs'd on him thoſe uſual Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that were wont to flow from his foul Tongue, turn'd him over to Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> with whom Mr. <hi>P.</hi> was to make his peace as well as he could. But though he could eaſily gueſs at what rate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101879:8"/>he might purchaſe his quiet, yet he did not think ſit to come up to the price; and ſo the Proſecution ſtill contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed depending till <hi>April</hi> 168<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, at which time a <hi>Ceſſat Proceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> was eaſily granted.</p>
            <p>I can't but think that all Scholars of that famous Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and eſpecially all Fellows of Colleges, will be Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates, and plead his Cauſe againſt Dr. <hi>H.</hi> For if a Pro-Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chancellor might expel him without ſo much as hearing him, it may concern them to conſider, that any Vicechancellor may in like manner turn out any of them, whenever the Expelling Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour ſhall take him; and what has been Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Caſe, may be their own.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion now is (and one would indeed wonder it ſhould be a queſtion) Whether Mr. <hi>P.</hi> who is already reſtor'd to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, ought to be reſtor'd to his Fellowip in <hi>Lincoln</hi> College? He thinks that he ought; thoſe of the College think otherwiſe: (which I confeſs is not very ſtrange, if one conſiders, that ſome of them were his Accuſers, and that one of them is in his Place.) Now there being this Controverſie between Him and Them, he apply'd himſelf (as the College-Statutes direct in ſuch Caſes) to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln;</hi> and having ſtated his Caſe, preſented it, <hi>May</hi> the 6th, to his Lordſhip then in <hi>London.</hi> He repreſented to his Lordſhip, <hi>That he was one of the Fellows of</hi> Lincoln <hi>College, nominated to a Fellowſhip there in</hi> 1674, <hi>by his Lordſhip's immediate Predeceſſor, Biſhop</hi> Fuller; <hi>That in</hi> 1683, <hi>he was Illegally and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarily expell'd the Univerſity by Dr.</hi> H. <hi>Pro-Vicechancellor; That the Rector and Fellows (taking it for granted, that an Expulſion from the Univerſity, whether juſt or unjuſt, imply'd an Expulſion from the College,) ſignify'd to his Lordſhip the vacancy of his Place: and that thereupon his Lordſhip (who has the right of nominating one to this Place, when vacant) forthwith nominated one Mr.</hi> Corniſh <hi>to it, who enjoy'd it till he died; and, after his deceaſe, one Mr.</hi> Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew, <hi>who enjoys it to this day.</hi> He did further ſet forth, <hi>That the Reverend Dr.</hi> Ironſide (<hi>late Vicechancellor of</hi> Oxford (<hi>now Lord Biſhop of</hi> Briſtol) <hi>had reſtor'd him to the Univirſity. And he humbly, conceiv'd, that thereupon he ought to be reſtor'd to his College, and to his Fellowſhip in it. For there never was</hi> (he ſaid) <hi>any other reaſon alledg'd to deprive him of the Profits of his Felloſhip in</hi> Lincoln <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, but only this, That being expelled the Univerſity, he was judg'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101879:8"/>uncapable of ſtaying in his College, and enjoying the Profits of his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip there; and that Reaſon now ceas'd; and therefore he hop'd, there being no Reaſon to keep him out of his Fellowſhip any longer, he ſhould forthwith be reſtor'd to it. He therefore humbly begg'd his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, who had nominated another to his Place, to make void that his Nomination, or rather to declare it void, (it being really void and null in the Conſtruction of the Law;) and thereby to make way for his return to his Fellowſhip in</hi> Lincoln <hi>College.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And afterwards, <hi>July</hi> the 16th, he wrote a Letter to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; then at <hi>Buckden;</hi> part of which I here preſent the Reader with, and that in his words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I humbly conceive, That your Lordſhip, as Viſitor of the College, may null or make void your nomination of another to my Place, upon good Information, That it was not well grounded at firſt; as, I believe, it now plainly appears to your Lordſhip that it was not. For your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's nomination of another to ſucceed me in my Fellowſhip, was ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Dr.</hi> H<hi>'s Expulſion of me, and a ſuppoſed vacancy ariſing from thence; and therefore your Lordſhip's nomination of another could be no more juſt, than Dr.</hi> H<hi>'s Expulſion of me was; nor could give ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any more right to my Place, than the Expulſion took from me: And I deſire no eaſier Thik than to prove, that the Expulſion was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and being ſuch, could not deprive me of the juſt Right I had to my Place in</hi> Lincoln <hi>College; (for no man ſhall loſe a juſt Right by the unjuſt Act of another:) and if it could not deprive me of my Right to my Fellowſhip in</hi> Lincoln <hi>College, then ſtill I have a right to it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Dr.</hi> H<hi>'s Expulſion of me; and he, who is at preſent in it, can have no right to it, notwithſtanding your Lordſhip's Nomination. And therefore I appeal to your Lordſhip as Viſitor of</hi> Lincoln <hi>College, and beſeech your Lordſhip to do me right. I leave it to your Lordſhip's Wiſdom, to take what method your Lordſhip ſhall think fit for the relieving of me: and if your Lordſhip thinks nothing leſs than a Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will no, I humbly deſire your Lordſhip to proceed to a Viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot ſay that theſe two Papers of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> did operate nothing on my Lord Biſhop; (for his Lordſhip declar'd himſelf to be clearly of opinion, That Mr. <hi>P.</hi> had hard meaſure, that he had been very unjuſtly treated, and that Dr. <hi>H.</hi> and thoſe of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, who had done him wrong, ought to make him ſatisfaction.) Yet this I muſt ſay, That though his Lordſhip receiv'd his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101879:9"/>yet (for what Reaſons I cannot tell) he has not yet thought fit to judge between the College and Him.</p>
            <p>It muſt be own'd by me, that the Rector and Fellows of <hi>Lincoln</hi> College have made ſome Objections againſt Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s reſtitution to his Fellowſhip: and it can't be deny'd by them, but every one of their Objections has had an Anſwer from him, though in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſome of them needed not any. They may print their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, if they liſt, and his Anſwers too, if they believe them ſuch as will ſerve to ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ff their Objections with advantage; but I have no room for Objections and Anſwers in this Paper. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to give the Reader a taſte of their Objections, I will men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one of them, and 'tis their great Objection in the Opinion of the Viſitor, that is, 'tis their greateſt they have. <hi>The great Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> (ſays his Lordſhip in a Letter directed to a Gentleman in <hi>London</hi>) <hi>that they have againſt Mr.</hi> P<hi>'s Reſtitution, is, That he neither had, nor ever asked leave to be abſent from College, which is Expulſion by their Statutes.</hi> And then his Lordſhip ſays how he had anſwer'd it: <hi>To this I told the Rector in a Letter, That Mr.</hi> P. <hi>was expell'd from the Univerſity, and not to come within five miles of it; and therefore could not come to the College to ask leave to be abſent.</hi> One would think that an expelled man ſhould rather have asked leave to ſtay in the College, than have begg'd leave to go away. Sure they were very hard put to it for Objections againſt Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, when ſuch as theſe were ſent from <hi>Oxford</hi> to <hi>Buckden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I given a ſhort and true Account of Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Caſe; my next Task is to vindicate him from the falſe Aſperſions that a late Author has caſt on him in his <hi>Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Author was pleas'd to ſay in his Preface, <hi>That he only did the Office of an Hiſtorian;</hi> but I'm ſure he has done it very ill in this particular that concerns Mr. <hi>P.</hi> however he has done it in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; which I do not intend to examine. The Office of an Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian I always thought had been to relate, and not to invent; but this Author has given too great a liberty to his Invention, there being not one jot of truth in his whole Story of Mr. <hi>P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can't but obſerve, that he uſhers in his falſe Tale of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> with another that is alſo falſe, and concerns a whole Convocation of Doctors and Maſters as well as him; for ſpeaking of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> paſt in their Convocation, <hi>July</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101879:9"/>the 21ſt, 1683. he ſays, <hi>That it-was ſubſcrib'd by the Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, other Profeſſors, and the whole Convocation.</hi> What the Vice-Chancellor and other Profeſſors did, I cannot tell; but I'm ſure, ſo far is it from being true, that it was ſubſcrib'd by the whole Convocation, that it was never ſo much as offer'd to the whole Convocation for their ſubſcription. But the Caſe was plainly this; <hi>The D. of</hi> Gloceſter, as this Author ſays, <hi>(and who elſe, or whether any elſe, I know not) drew up a Decree, in which ſeveral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions were condemned as falſe, ſeditious, and impious; and ſeveral Bocks quoted, in which it was ſaid the Propoſitions condemned were contain'd: but none of the Convocation beſides the Perſon or Perſons concern'd in drawing up the Decree, had any time given to examine the truth either of the Propoſitions, or of the Quotations. But the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per drawn up was read in the Convocation houſe, and 'twas imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately put to the Vote, whether it ſhould paſs, or no; the Zealous Men cry'd out,</hi> Placet; <hi>and others thought not fit to make oppoſition: and ſo out they came from the Convocation, and preſently a fire being kindled in the Court of the Schools, the naughty Books were burnt by the hand of the Marſhall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having abus'd a Convocation of Doctors, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, he ſingles out Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and falls foul upon him. And pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to this Decree, <hi>Parkinſon, a Fellow of</hi> Lincoln <hi>College, for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, That the right and foundation of all Power was in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; That Kings are accountable for their Male-adminiſtrati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And particularly, That King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt was juſtly put to dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h for making war upon his Subjects; was, Ann.</hi> 1684. <hi>expell'd the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place, He is miſtaken as to the time of Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion (which is not ſeemly in one that pretends to do the Office of an Hiſtorian) for he was not expell'd in 1684. (as this Author ſays) but in 1683. But this Miſtake I eaſily forgive, becauſe, I belleve it was againſt his will; and will only deſire the Reader from hence to obſerve, how little this Hiſtorian underſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'s Caſe, and how unfit he was to repreſent it.</p>
            <p>But he is guilty of a far worſe Miſtake, in aſſigning the Cauſe of the Expulſion; and this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I doubt, was a wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul Miſtake, and therefore juſtly deſerves blame. He mentions Three Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101879:10"/>1. <hi>That the right and foundation of all Power is in the Poeple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That Kings are accountable for their Male-adminiſtration,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>And particularly, That King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt,</hi> &amp;c. And ſays that <hi>P.</hi> was expelled the Univerſity for maintaining of theſe Three, with an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he was pleas'd to add to the tail of the Second Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and by which he would have his Reader underſtand a great many more Propoſitions than he was willing to expreſs. As for his <hi>Et coetera's,</hi> I have nothing to ſay to 'em; for I know not what, nor how many they are, any more than he does. But as for the Three Propoſitions that he has mention'd, I do aver it is ſo far from being true, that <hi>P.</hi> was Expell'd for all, or any of them, that it was never ſo much as objected, or laid to his Charge, That he had maintain'd any one of them: And I challenge this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, whoever he is, to produce any Authority for what he has with ſo much confidence aſſerted. The Indictment (as is plain to any one that reads it) will not help him out; for though therein mention be made of Three Propoſitions, yet not one of thoſe Three in the Indictment is the ſame with any one of theſe mention'd in the <hi>Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</hi> A Copy of the <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus,</hi> or Expulſion, will ſtand him in as little ſtead; for though that mentions that <hi>P.</hi> was expelled for uttering reproachful Words againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, yet it does not expreſs in particular what they were. I am reſolv'd to be civil to this Author, and therefore I'll give him leave to go to Dr. <hi>H.</hi> the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peller, and ask him, what he expell'd <hi>P.</hi> for. I know well enough what Anſwer he will give: He will ſay, That an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was exhibited againſt <hi>P.</hi> That the Grand-Jury had found the Bill; That he from thence concluded that <hi>P.</hi> was guilty; That thereupon, without any more ado, he proceeded to expel him; it being needleſs to try one, whom he believed to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And if you object any thing againſt this way of proceeding, as not agreeable to Law, then preſently out he pulls his <hi>Orders from above,</hi> and this anſwers all Objections. This he formerly ſaid, and this I'm apt to think he will ſtill ſay; and if he does, 'tis plain that he charges <hi>P.</hi> with nothing but what was in the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and conſequently not with any of theſe Three Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that are mentioned in the <hi>Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I'll give Dr. <hi>H.</hi> leave to give what Anſwer he pleaſes;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101879:10"/>(though, I believe, he had much rather I would give him leave to hold his Tongue) I'll give him leave to ſay what this Author would have him, That he expell'd <hi>P.</hi> for maintaining theſe very Propoſitions that are mention'd in the <hi>Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</hi> But then I expect, that he ſhould be ſo civil as to anſwer the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Queries: Why did he not mention theſe Propoſitions in the Indictment? Why not in the <hi>Bannimus?</hi> Why did he not at leaſt particularly mention that Third Propoſition, which this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has mention'd in ſo particular a manner? Why did he not take care to publiſh this to the World, and that too with the higheſt aggravations, out of mere regard to his own Credit, and for vindicating the Severity of his own Proceedings, which moſt men thought were unjuſt? One would think it was very nigh as bad to affirm, <hi>That King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt was juſtly put to death,</hi> as 'twas to hold, <hi>That his Son the Duke might be excluded:</hi> and why then was this latter mention'd in the Indictment, and not the former? To conclude, If Dr. <hi>H.</hi> knew any thing, ſix years ago, of <hi>P</hi>'s maintaining theſe Three Propoſitions, why did he then conceal it? And if he knew nothing of it, how could he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel him for it?</p>
            <p>I have, I hope, ſufficiently vindicated <hi>P.</hi> from the miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Author; and I think I need ſay no more about it; but I have not yet done with the Author himſelf: I find him a peeviſh Man, and I'm unwilling to leave him as I find him, and therefore I'll try, if I can, to put him into good humour. And becauſe there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he ſeems to like more than his Paſſive-Obedience, or Non-reſiſtance (tho I am apt to think, he likes it ſomewhat leſs in this, than he did in the former Reign) I will, to pleaſe him, give it under my hand, That if he will ſtill be for his Paſſive-Obedience in the preſent Reign, I will not oppoſe him; (and it may be I may get Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> to ſubſcribe the ſame) not that I think it a true Doctine any more now, than 'twas in the two late Reigns, but becauſe I am perſuaded that 'tis now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come innocent, and will do no harm; for a Doctrine can do no harm when 'tis not believed: and neither King nor people will believe this Doctrine any longer. The late King <hi>James</hi> had ſufficient experience of this Principle of Paſſive Obedience to his coſt; and our preſent King is more Wiſe, and more Juſt,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101879:11"/>than to make tryal of it: And the people, I tro, will never more be fond of a Doctrine that renders their beings uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable in this World, ſince their Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itual Paſtors are now of opinion, that they may get to Heaven without it. And, God be thanked, we are like to hear this Doctrine from the Pulpits no more; for they that have ſworn Allegiance to King <hi>William,</hi> can't with any Grace Preach up a Doctrine that directly tends to dethrone him, by condemning all thoſe that invited him hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and aſſiſted him here, and ſet the Crown on his head: And they who have not ſworn, and will not ſwear Allegiance to him, are never like to have any Pulpits to Preach in; unleſs the King and Parliament ſhould, by an Act of Grace, think fit to indulge thoſe, who declare themſelves enemies to the preſent Conſtitution. So that, as far as I can ſee, this Doctrine of Paſſive-Obedience, and Non-reſiſtance, muſt take ſhelter in Conventicles; (I mean new and upſtart Conventicles; for the old ones, I believe, will not receive it, unleſs one can imagine that they like it any whit the better, becauſe it now brings a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial from a late dying Biſhop): This Doctrine, I ſay, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be thought by ſome to be the Characteriſtick of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> muſt creep into private Meetings, and be Preach'd up in a Tub; And I hope that both Preachers and Hearers of this Doctrine will be few, and (a temper being ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found out to reconcile the Diſſenters to our Church) the only Conventiclers in the Nation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Hiſtory of Moſt Illuſtrious <hi>William,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> Deduc'd from the firſt Founders of the Ancient Houſe of <hi>Naſſau:</hi> Together with the moſt conſiderable Actions of this preſent Prince. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Collection of Fourteen Papers, Relating to the Affiairs of Church and State, in the Reign of the late King <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Character of a Trimmer. His Opinion of I. The Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. II. Proteſtant Religion. III. The Papiſts. IV. Foreign Affairs. By the Honourable Sir <hi>W. Conventry.</hi> The Third Edition, carefully Corrected, and cleared from the Errors of the firſt Impreſſion.</item>
               <item>An Impartial, Relation of the Illegal Proceedings againſt St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> College in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1687. Containing only Matters of Fact as they occurred. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi> To which is added the moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Paſſages, omitted in the former, by reaſon of the Severity of the Preſs. Collected by a Fellow of the ſaid College.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
